What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Don’t tell me you haven’t
put some serious thought
on how to avoid dementia:
a brain disease that has
no real cure as of yet.
Here’s our first story.
Although it's known that
plant-based foods are important
for physical health,
less is known about
the relationship between plant-
based foods and cognitive health.
Now in terms of preventing Alzheimer's
and other forms of actual dementia,
there's data that those who consume
meat, including poultry and fish,
have 2 to 3 times the risk
of developing dementia
compared with vegetarians,
but what about just like
day-to-day function?
Greater adherence to a more
plant-based dietary pattern
was related to better
performance on all cognitive
tasks researchers measured.
One possible mechanism that
could have been thought
to underlie the results
is body weight. I mean,
plant-based diets reduce BMI,
and lower BMI has been associated
with better cognitive function,
but they still found a connection
between more plants
and better brain function
even after controlling for weight.
Another possible mechanism linking
diet and cognition is inflammation.
That's how saturated fat impairs
the memory of lab rats,
through brain inflammation.
And since fiber can be
anti-inflammatory, and
meat pro-inflammatory,
that may help explain some
effects of plant-based diets
on health and cognition.
The saturated fat connection appears
to extend to human cognition.
A systematic review and
meta-analysis covering nine studies
found that increased
saturated fat intake,
which is found mostly
in meat, dairy, and junk,
was associated with a 40% increased
risk of cognitive impairment
and nearly 90% higher risk
of Alzheimer's disease.
So wait, does that mean if you
put people on a low-carb diet,
it impairs their brain function?
Yes, it does.
A high-fat diet not only impairs the
heart but also cognitive function.
Men were randomized to just
to 5 days of a high-fat,
low-carbohydrate diet,
or a lower fat diet,
and on the low-carb diet
cognitive tests showed
they suffered impaired attention,
speed, and mood.
Again, just within days.
Conclusion: raising the level of fat
in your blood not only decreased
energy production in the heart,
but reduced cognition, which
suggests that a high-fat diet is
detrimental to the heart and brain.
Now they were thinking
the impaired energy production
may have accounted for
the brain dysfunction as well,
but oral glycotoxins may
also link high-fat eating with
a loss of cognitive capacity.
Glycotoxins, also known as advanced
glycation end products or AGEs,
are a class of oxidant
stress-promoting agents,
free radical-promoting agents
implicated in diabetes and aging,
including brain injury due to
Alzheimer's disease and stroke.
The development of Alzheimer's
disease in the first place
is thought to involve the
accumulation of these AGEs,
which encourage the formation
and deposition of the two
hallmarks of Alzheimer's:
neurofibrillary tangles and
amyloid plaques in the brain,
discovered on autopsy.
But it's not just full-blown
dementia. Evidence suggests
AGEs contribute to
cognitive decline in general.
Dietary advanced glycation
end products are associated
with a decline in memory.
And since modifying the levels
of AGEs in the diet
may be relatively easy,
these preliminary results
suggest a simple strategy
to diminish cognitive compromise.
What are the major sources of
dietary AGEs to stay away from?
Meat, cooked using high,
dry heat, such as in broiling,
grilling, frying, and roasting.
From my video, "The Best Diet
for Healthy Aging,"
here is the list of all the most
AGE-contaminated foods.
AGEs are not only associated with
getting Alzheimer's in the first place,
but also the progression
of Alzheimer's disease,
as well as lower cognitive
performance in general,
as tracked, interestingly enough,
via skin autofluorescence.
AGE's have a natural fluorescence
that you can pick up
using a special detector, enabling
a simple non-invasive assessment
of advanced glycation end product
accumulation in the body.
The more meat you eat, the more
of the AGE skin autofluorescence
you get, which then correlates
with cognitive impairment.
In fact one of these days
these fluorescence scanners
may be included in
routine medical check-ups.
Since meat is the main high
AGE-food, it should be no surprise
that AGE skin autofluorescence
measurements are
significantly lower in those
eating more plant based.
So the data suggest reduction
of food-derived AGEs is feasible
and may provide effective
treatment strategies
for our epidemics of Alzheimer's
and metabolic disease.
In our next story, we look at
the best source of lutein,
the primary carotenoid
antioxidant in the brain.
There's an extensive scientific
literature describing the positive
impact of dietary plant compounds
on overall health and longevity.
However, it's only now becoming
clear that the consumption of diets
rich in plant foods can influence neuro-
inflammation, brain inflammation,
leading to the expression of
cytoprotective, cell protective,
and restorative proteins.
Just over the last decade, remarkable
progress has been made
to realize that oxidative stress and
chronic, low-grade inflammation,
are major risk factors
underlying brain aging,
so no wonder antioxidant and
anti-inflammatory foods may help.
The brain is especially vulnerable to
free radical attack, oxidative stress,
due to its high fat content and its
cauldron of high metabolic activity.
You don't want your
brains to go rancid.
So you'd think one of the major
fat-soluble dietary antioxidants
like beta-carotene would step in, but
the major carotenoid concentrated
in the brain is actually lutein; the
brain just preferentially sucks it up.
For example, if you
look at the oldest old,
like in the Georgia
centenarian study,
recognizing that oxidation is involved
in age-related cognitive decline,
they figured dietary antioxidants may
play a role in its prevention or delay,
so they looked at eight different ones,
vitamin A, vitamin E, on down the list,
and only lutein was significantly
related to better cognition.
Now in this study they looked
at brain tissue on autopsy.
By then it's a little too late.
So how could you study
the effects of diet
on the brain while
you're still alive?
If only there was a way we
could physically look into
the living brain with
our own two eyes.
There is!
With our own two eyes.
The retina, the back of our eyeball,
is actually an extension
of our central nervous system,
an outpouching of the brain
during development, and right
in the middle there's a spot.
This is what the doctor sees
when they look into your eye
with that bright light.
That spot, called the macula,
is our HD camera, where you get
the highest resolution vision,
and it's packed with lutein.
And indeed, levels in the retina
correspond to levels
in the rest of your brain,
so your eyes can be a
window into your brain.
So now we can finally do
studies on live people
to see if diet can affect
lutein levels in the eyes,
which reflects lutein
levels in the brain,
and see if that correlates with
improvements in cognitive function.
And indeed, significant correlations
exist between the amount
of macular pigment, these
plant pigments like lutein
in your eye, and
cognitive test scores.
You can demonstrate this
on functional MRI scans,
suggesting lutein and a related
plant pigment called zeaxanthin
promote cognitive functioning in old
age by enhancing neural efficiency,
the efficiency by which
our nerves communicate.
Like check out this cool study
on white matter integrity
using something called
diffusion tensor imaging,
which provides unique insights
into brain network connectivity,
allowing you to follow the nerve
tracts throughout the brain.
And researchers were able to
show enhanced circuit integrity
based on how much lutein and zeaxanthin
they could see in people's eyes—
further evidence of a meaningful
relationship between diet and integrity
of our brains, particularly in regions
vulnerable to age-related decline.
So do Alzheimer's patients have
less of this macular pigment?
Significantly less lutein in their eyes,
significantly less lutein in their blood,
and a higher occurrence
of macular degeneration,
where this pigment layer
gets destroyed.
The thickness of this plant pigment
layer in your eyes can be measured
and may be a potential marker
for the beginnings of Alzheimer's.
Let's not wait that long, though.
We know macular pigment density
is related to cognitive function
in older people.
What about during middle age?
One apparent consequence of aging
appears to be loss of some aspects
of cognitive control, which starts
out early, in mid-adulthood,
but not in everybody, suggesting
maybe something like diet could
be driving some of the differences.
Here's a measure of cognitive control,
showing younger, on average,
do better than older adults.
But older adults who have
high macular pigment,
lots of lutein in the back of their
eyes, do significantly better.
These results suggest that the
protective role of carotenoids
like lutein within the brain
may be evident during
early and middle adulthood,
decades prior to the onset of more
apparent cognitive decline later in life.
You can take 20-year-olds and
show superior auditory function
in those with more macular
pigment in their eyes.
Look, the auditory system,
our hearing, like the rest
of the central nervous system,
is ultimately constructed
and maintained by diet, and
it is therefore, not surprisingly,
sensitive to dietary intake
throughout life,
all the way back to childhood.
Higher macular pigment is associated
with higher academic achievement
among school children.
You can look into a kid's eyes
and get some sense of how well
they may do in subjects
like math and writing.
This finding is important because
macular lutein is modifiable
and can be manipulated
by dietary intake.
OK, OK, so where is lutein found?
The avocado and egg
industries like to boast
about how much of these macular
pigments they have in their products,
but the real superstars
are dark green leafy vegetables.
A half cup of kale has 50
times more than an egg,
a spinach salad,
or a 50-egg omelet?
And the earlier the better.
Pregnant and breastfeeding women
should definitely be checking off
my Daily Dozen greens servings.
But it's also apparently
never too late.
While some age-related cognitive
decline is to be expected,
these effects may be less pronounced
among those eating more green and leafy.
Finally today, avocados, greens,
and lutein and zeaxanthin supplements
are put to the test for
improving cognitive function.
Dark green leafy vegetables are packed
with a brain antioxidant called lutein.
And so increasing our greens intake could
be an important public health strategy
for reducing the risk of visual
or cognitive impairment.
Lutein is the dominant
dietary pigment
in the retina of the eye
as well as the brain.
And so not surprising
that macular pigment—
the concentration of lutein in the
center of your eye called the macula—
was found to be significantly
correlated with levels in the brain,
which may explain the link between
how much of these greens nutrients
you can see in the back of
the eye and cognitive function.
The neuroprotection is assumed
to be because lutein is
such a powerful antioxidant, but it
also has anti-inflammatory properties.
This relationship between lutein,
and another greens
nutrient called zeaxanthin,
and visual and cognitive health
throughout the lifespan is compelling.
But that was based on observational
studies, where you observe
that higher lutein levels and brain
function seem to go together,
but you don't know if it's cause
and effect until you put it to the test.
Could lutein and zeaxanthin
be supplemented
as part of a lifestyle intervention
to both improve brain function
and reduce the probability
of slipping into dementia?
The reason everyone is so
excited about the possibility
is because of the hopeful data
from eye health studies
that have convinced many
ophthalmologists to start recommending
people start increasing their lutein
and zeaxanthin intake to prevent
and treat macular degeneration, a
leading cause of age-related vision loss.
You don't have to take pills, though.
Adding as little as 60 grams
of spinach a day for a month—
that's like one-fifth of a 10-ounce
package of frozen spinach—
can significantly boost macular
pigment in most people.
And it not just good for
treating diseased eyes.
A randomized, placebo-controlled study
found that these greens goodies
can improve visual processing
speed in young healthy people.
That's like when you're trying to
hit a fastball and your body
has to start reacting before you
even consciously register it—
with real-world benefits
outside the major leagues,
improving, for example,
visual driving performance.
OK, but what about cognition?
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial of adults,
average age 73, given the equivalent
of about a half cup a day's worth
of cooked kale, or a full
cup of cooked spinach,
and got significant improvements
in cognitive function
compared to those randomized
to the placebo.
It may even work in young
adults too, average age 21.
Daily supplementation with that same
amount of lutein and zeaxanthin
not only increased their macular pigment,
but resulted in significant improvements
in brain function—spatial memory,
reasoning ability, and complex attention.
Have they ever tried putting
whole foods to the test?
Hard to get Americans
to eat greens every day,
but not so hard to get them
to eat guacamole.
This study tested the effects of the
intake of avocado on cognition,
a six-month, randomized,
controlled trial.
What was the control?
One avocado a day, or a potato
or a cup of chickpeas,
and those in the avocado group
had a significant improvement
in cognitive function.
But to the Avocado Board's chagrin,
so did the tater and chickpea group.
That's the problem with
having healthy placebos.
Maybe they should have used
iceberg lettuce or something.
What about the impact on cognition
of those who really need it,
Alzheimer's disease patients?
Their vision got better, that's good,
but no significant changes
in cognitive function.
Now it's possible that eating whole
foods, like dark green leafies,
might have worked better than
just the pigments in pill form.
Yes, oxidation and inflammation
appear to be key to both Alzheimer's
and macular degeneration, but neither
disease seems particularly amenable
to late-stage treatments.
That's why prevention is the key.
Reducing oxidation and
inflammation in the earliest stages
may be our most promising approach.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.